Yousuf Motiwala Data Scientist

✓ yousuf.s.motiwala@gmail.com

+919029506876

in Yousuf Motiwala

YousufM

Profile Summary

Senior Data Scientist specialised in Strategy Consulting with 5 years of experience in helping decision-makers in driving actionable insights from data. Successfully assisted CXOs across industries such as Consumer-Retail, Telco, IG, Public-Sector & Media to achieve business objectives using Machine Learning & advanced analytics. Aspiring for a new opportunity where I'd be able to lead teams and data science initiatives to bring tangible business impact.

Professional Experience

Boston Consulting Group

Senior Data Analyst

- Developed outbound acquisition strategy for SaaS provider leveraging Customer Segmentation & Propensity Modelling, resulting in additional 20% win-rate
- Assisted Central Gov. in designing, one of its kind in the world, a national-level agricultural land X farmer database; the case was presented to Prime Minister's Office

Data Analyst

- Feb 2021 Dec 2022 • Devised a Price Optimization Algorithm for a semiconductor manufacturer, leveraging Bangalore, India price-elasticity and LR to identify an additional 20% revenue opportunity.
- Added a new BCG capability on non-linear optimisation that identifies optimal transport frequency based on operational, waiting time & crowding cost
- Built a Credit Risk ML model in R that buckets applications based on predicted risk and reduced 30% of the manual screening workload for an India-based NBFC
- Developed M&A strategy by identifying P&Ls & market viewership synergies that generated an additional 7% profit opportunity for India's largest Media merger.
- Developed a predictive ML model to identify profit drivers & set branch strategy to untapped additional 25% profit opportunity for a leading national bank

Nielsen

Executive – Business Insights (Retail & FMCG)

- Designed 3 Annual retail sales Brand Plans for India's third-largest beverage firm; won "Simply Excellent award" & generated an additional 5% revenue opportunity
- · Mentored three associates, and led a team of five on pack-price-distribution strategy for India's largest snacking brand. Unlocked additional 0.3% growth opportunity

Analyst - Business Insights (FMCG)

- Identified pack & channel optimisation strategy for a leading Juice brand, resulting in an additional 1.5% share gain opportunity
- Designed case study on "Revamping distribution through Product Innovation" for India's leading FMCG firm. Achieved "Exceeds Expectations" for the analyses

Apr 2017 - Jul 2018

Aug 2018 - Aug 2019

Mumbai, India

Jan 2023 - present

Bangalore, India

Mumbai, India

Education

MSc Business Analytics - Specialized in Applied ML - Distinction

Bayes Business School (Triple Crown Accreditation)

2019 - 2020 London, UK

Vodafone UK:

Data Scientist - MSc Dissertation - 6 months

 Developed a Ranking Methodology to prioritize locations for 5G investment using Geo-Clustering ML algorithms

Bachelor of Management Studies

Hinduja College (NAAC accredited "A+")

CGPA: 6.4/7.0 (**Top 10%**)

2013 - 2016

Mumbai, India

Skills

- **Business Intelligence:** Price Optimisation, Promotion Effectiveness, Demand / Sales / Inventory Forecasting, Customer Churn Prediction, Credit Risk Modelling, Customer Segmentation, Route & Capacity Optimisation
- **Technique Stack:** Predictive Machine Learning, Linear & Non-Linear Optimisation, Time-series forecasting, Data Engineering, Geo-spatial modelling & NLP
- Tools: Python, R, SQL, Alteryx, Tableau, Power BI, Advance MS Excel (VBA), AWS Sagemaker, PySpark

Awards & Certifications

- BCG: Olympics 2021 best cases Finalist (NAMR) For the Lighthouse project
- Nielsen: Simply Excellent Silver for delivering actionable insights to the client's sales team
- Nielsen: Simply Excellent Bronze for exemplifying client-centricity
- NIIT 3 Yrs Diploma certificate in Data Science (CGPA: 9.0/10.0)

Langauges

Fluent in English, Gujarati, Urdu and Hindi; Intermediate in Arabic